Atlantic Union Committee Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Atlantic Union Committee Records 1940-1968 (bulk 1949-1952)
MSS11304
Atlantic Union Committee
39,500 items 136 containers 54 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Organization to foster a union of Atlantic democracies. Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, financial records, office administrative files, chapter files, printed materials, and other records relating to the organization and its activities.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Agar, Herbert, 1897-1980--Correspondence.; Bishop, Robert J. (Robert Jefferson), 1913- --Correspondence.; Blackwelder, Justin--Correspondence.; Clayton, Will, 1880-1966--Correspondence.; Curtis, Lionel, 1872-1955--Correspondence.; Dennis, Donald P. (Donald Philips), 1916- --Correspondence.; Edson, C. A.--Correspondence.; Flower, Henry C.--Correspondence.; Garwood, Ellen, 1903- --Correspondence.; Gillette, Guy M. (Guy Mark), 1879-1973--Correspondence.; Hartley, Livingston, 1900- --Correspondence.; Head, Henry William Nugent, 1898-1964. Henry William Nugent Head papers. 1940-1955.; Henry, Gerald B.--Correspondence.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978--Correspondence.; Ives, Irving McNeil, 1896-1962--Correspondence.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973--Correspondence.; Kefauver, Estes, 1903-1963--Correspondence.; Meeman, Edward J. (Edward John), 1889-1966--Correspondence.; Moore, Hugh, 1887-1972--Correspondence.; Moore, Walden--Correspondence.; Orgill, Edmund--Correspondence.; Osborn, Stellanova, 1894-1988--Correspondence.; Osborne, Lithgow, 1892-1980--Correspondence.; Patterson, Robert Porter, 1891-1952--Correspondence.; Roberts, Owen J. (Owen Josephus), 1875-1955--Correspondence.; Roper, Elmo, 1900-1971--Correspondence.; Streit, Clarence K. (Clarence Kirshman), 1896-1986--Correspondence.
Organizations
Atlantic Union Committee.; United States. Congress --Resolutions.
Subjects
International organization.; Internationalism--Societies, etc.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The records of the Atlantic Union Committee were given to the Library of Congress in 1964 by Clarence K. Streit and in 1965 by Ruth Nugent Head. Additional installments were given in 1983 by Justin Blackwelder and in 1988 by Mrs. Clarence K. Streit.
Related Material
A related collection in the Manuscript Division is the
Clarence K. Streit Papers
.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Atlantic Union Committee span the years 1940-1968, with the bulk of the material from 1949 to 1952. The Atlantic Union Committee was organized in 1949 by Justice Owen J. Roberts as an independent committee of Federal Union, Inc., formed in 1939 by Clarence K. Streit, author of Union Now, published in the same year. The goal of the committee was to persuade the United States Congress to pass a resolution calling for a federal convention, like the one in Philadelphia in 1787, to explore the possibility of union among the Atlantic democracies of North America and Europe. The Atlantic Union Committee was dissolved in 1961 without having achieved its goal. The collection is arranged in four parts as described below.
Part I
Part I of the Atlantic Union Committee Records spans the years 1940-1968, with the bulk of the material concentrated from 1949 to 1952. Files in Part I include correspondence, reports, memoranda, financial records, general office administrative files, and miscellany. The material relates primarily to the organization, structure, and general activities of the Atlantic Union Committee, its chapter activities, and the resolutions it submitted to Congress between 1949 and 1952. The principal correspondents include Herbert Agar, Robert J. Bishop, Justin Blackwelder, Will Clayton, Donald P. Dennis, C. A. Edson, Henry C. Flower, Ellen (Mrs. St. John) Garwood, Guy M. Gillette, Livingston Hartley, Gerald B. Henry, Estes Kefauver, Edward J. Meeman, Hugh Moore, Walden Moore, Edmund Orgill, Stellanova (Mrs. Chase S.) Osborn, Lithgow Osborne, Robert Porter Patterson, Owen J. Roberts, Elmo Roper, and Clarence K. Streit. Within the correspondence related to the congressional comment on the Atlantic Union resolution are letters to and from Senators Hubert H. Humphrey, Irving McNeil Ives, and Lyndon B. Johnson.
Part II
Part II of the records spans the years 1940-1955, with the bulk from 1950 to 1953, consisting of the personal papers of Henry William Nugent Head (1898-1964), British subject and friend of the Atlantic Union Committee. It reflects Head's role as secretary of the Atlantic Affiliates and the Atlantic Union Committee's desire to build an overseas base. Subject files in this portion include correspondence with Atlantic affiliates and committee agents in European countries and Canada such as Lionel Curtis. Head's papers also contain personal correspondence, minutes of meetings, articles and reprints, and books and clippings.
Part III
Part III of the collection consists chiefly of correspondence and transcripts, but also includes reports, memoranda, minutes, financial records, printed matter, newspaper clippings, and related items. This material deals primarily with the efficacy of convincing Congress to pass a resolution inviting representatives from Western democracies to meet and explore the possibilities of forming a free federal union that would strive to prevent the spread of communism without resorting to war. Dating from 1946 to 1968, the bulk of the addition covers the years 1950-1958. Most of the correspondence is with members of the committee and from members of Congress, some of whom were cited previously.
Part IV
The records of Part IV span the years 1946-1960, with the bulk from 1949 to 1956. The majority of this part consists of committee correspondence and memoranda pertaining chiefly to the organization's efforts to get an Atlantic union resolution passed in Congress. Also included is information about the establishment of the Atlantic Union Committee and minutes of its annual congresses and work conferences.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is composed of eleven series arranged in four parts:
Part I:
General Office File, 1949-1960
Correspondence and Related Material, 1943-1960
Chapter File, 1949-1954
Atlantic Union Resolution: Congressional Comment, 1949-1952
Miscellany, 1948-1960
Part II:
Henry William Nugent Head Papers, 1940-1955
Part III:
General Correspondence, 1949-1968
Subject File, 1947-1968
Speeches and Statements, 1948-1967
Miscellany, 1949-1967
Part IV:
Subject File, 1946-1960
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm81011304
Container List
- Part I: General Office File, 1949-1960 (Box 1-9)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter, newspaper clippings, and related material.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - American Assembly, 1951 (Box 1)
  - American Association for United Nations, 1951-1953
  - American Award, 1951
  - American Committee on United Europe, 1949-1951
  - American Jewish Committee, 1951
  - American Legion, 1951
  - Atlantic Affiliates Committee, 1950-1952
  - Atlantic Award, 1952
  - Atlantic Commission bill, 1951-1952
  - Atlantic Congress, Kenneth Lindsay Plan, 1951
  - Atlantic Institute, 1960
  - Atlantic Union Committee (Box 2)
    - Council, 1951
    - Executive Committee, 1953
    - Field work, 1951-1952
    - General, 1949-1958, (6 folders)
    - Organization, 1949
    - Stamp, 1950 (Box 3)
    - Symbol, 1949
  - Atlantic Union News, 1949-1952
  - Board of governors
    - Biographies, 1949-1951
    - Correspondence, 1949-1953, (4 folders)
    - General, 1949-1960
    - Nominations, 1950-1951
    - Canada, 1950-1952, (2 folders)
  - Chapter keymen, 1951-1952 (Box 4)
  - Chapter releases, 1950-1951
  - Committee materials, 1949-1951
  - Committee on the Present Danger, 1950-1952
  - Congressional action and election, 1949-1950
  - Congressional Record, 1950-1952
  - Contacts, 1949
  - Crackpot letters, 1949-1952
  - Dangers in European union, 1951-1952
  - Department changes in procedure, 1951-1952
  - Dinners, Washington, D.C., 1951-1958
  - Directors, Executive Committee, 1949-1951
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., letter, 1951 (Box 5)
  - European union, 1949-1951
  - Federal Union, Inc., 1949-1953, (2 folders)
  - Hartley, Livingston, article, 1950-1951
  - “Here's Now,” 1951-1952
  - Labor, 1950-1951
  - Legal Committee, 1949-1950
  - Lettershop instructions, 1952, (2 folders)
  - Library list, 1950
  - Literature Committee, 1951-1952, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Literature and publication, 1949-1952, (4 folders)
  - Lobbying, 1949-1952, (2 folders)
  - London Sunday Times and Louisville Courier Journal, 1951-1952
  - Mailing list, 1960 (Box 7)
  - “March of Time,” 1950-1952
  - Memphis, Tenn., manifesto, 1951
  - Movie, fund and project, 1950-1953, (6 folders)
  - National Information Bureau, 1951 (Box 8)
  - New England Council & Atlantic Union Committee, proposed field organization, 1952
  - Office memoranda, 1950-1952
  - Political committee, 1949-1952, (3 folders)
  - Press releases and reports, 1950-1952, (2 folders)
  - Progress report pamphlet, 1952
  - Public relations (Box 9)
    - Projects, 1952
    - Reports, 1949-1950
  - Publicity chairman
    - Correspondence, 1951-1952
    - Projects, 1950-1951
  - Radio reports, 1949-1952, (3 folders)
  - Resolutions, 1949-1951
  - Speaker's bureau, 1949-1951
  - Speeches, 1951
  - State Department, 1950-1951
  - United Nations Economic and Social Council, Atlantic Union Committee application for consultative status, 1950
- Part I: Correspondence and Related Material, 1943-1960 (Box 10-18)
  Letters, telegrams, memoranda, reports, and related material. Arranged chronologically within four categories: congressional, foreign, press, radio, and general.
  The general correspondence file is arranged alphabetically in two chronological subsets, 1943-1954 and 1960.
  - Congressional, 1951-1952, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Foreign, 1949-1952, (2 folders)
  - Press, 1951-1952, (4 folders)
  - Radio, 1949-1952, (5 folders) (Box 11)
  - General, 1943-1954
    - A-C, (14 folders)
    - D-G, (17 folders) (Box 12)
    - H-M, (24 folders) (Box 13)
    - O-R, (20 folders) (Box 14)
    - R-Y, (18 folders) (Box 15)
  - General, 1960 (Box 16)
    - A-H, (9 folders)
    - I-O, (11 folders) (Box 17)
    - P-Y, (11 folders) (Box 18)
- Part I: Chapter File, 1949-1954 (Box 19-33)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and routine administrative and financial records relating to the organization and administrative activities of the chapters.
  Arranged alphabetically by state and local chapter, respectively, and chronologically within each chapter.
  - General, (5 folders) (Box 19)
  - Alabama-California, (16 folders)
  - California-Colorado, (12 folders) (Box 20)
  - Connecticut-District of Columbia, (11 folders) (Box 21)
  - Florida-Illinois, (22 folders) (Box 22)
  - Illinois-Iowa, (15 folders) (Box 23)
  - Kansas-Maryland, (28 folders) (Box 24)
  - Massachusetts-Michigan, (27 folders) (Box 25)
  - Michigan-Nevada, (16 folders) (Box 26)
  - New Hampshire-New York, (15 folders) (Box 27)
  - New York, (13 folders) (Box 28)
  - New-York-Oklahoma, (21 folders) (Box 29)
  - Oregon-Pennsylvania, (17 folders) (Box 30)
  - Rhode Island-Texas, (15 folders) (Box 31)
  - Texas-Utah, (11 folders) (Box 32)
  - Vermont-Wyoming, (16 folders) (Box 33)
- Part I: Atlantic Union Resolution: Congressional Comment, 1949-1952 (Box 34-39)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and related material pertaining to the joint resolution before the United States Congress favoring the creation of the Atlantic Union with the United States as a member.
  The material is arranged alphabetically by state and therein by name of member of Congress.
  - Alabama-Florida, (16 folders) (Box 34)
  - Georgia-Maryland, (19 folders) (Box 35)
  - Massachusetts-New Hampshire, (15 folders) (Box 36)
  - New Jersey-New York, (15 folders) (Box 37)
  - North Carolina-South Dakota, (14 folders) (Box 38)
  - Texas-Wyoming, (12 folders) (Box 39)
- Part I: Miscellany, 1948-1960 (Box 40-41)
  Financial records, printed matter, newspaper clippings, and other miscellaneous material.
  Grouped by type of material.
  - Clippings, 1949-1960 (Box 40)
  - Financial papers
    - Advertisements, 1949-1950
    - Budget, 1949-1952, (5 folders)
    - Chapter reports and refunds, 1951-1953
    - Finance Committee, 1949-1951, (4 folders)
    - Financial campaign, 1952-1953, (2 folders)
    - Financial statements, 1949-1960 (Box 41)
    - Payroll records, 1953-1961
    - Salaries, 1951-1952
    - Special projects, 1951
  - General, 1950-1954
  - Printed matter, 1948-1955
- Part II: Henry William Nugent Head Papers, 1940-1955 (Box 42-53)
  Subject files containing correspondence, transcripts, minutes of meetings, articles and reprints, clippings, and other printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization, topic, or type of material.
  - Agar, Herbert Sebastian, 1950-1953 (Box 42)
  - Atlantic Affiliates Committee
    - Correspondence
      - 1950-1951, (6 folders)
      - 1952 (Box 43)
    - Minutes and activities, 1950-1952
  - Belgium, 1950-1953
  - Board of governors, 1952
  - Bulletins, 1949-1952
  - Canada (Box 44)
    - Conference, 1952
    - Correspondence, 1950-1952
    - Miscellany, 1949-1952
  - Cavell, R. G., 1950-1951
  - Clippings
    - Churchill, Sir Winston, 1948-1951, undated
    - General, 1950-1952, (4 folders)
    - “Today and Tomorrow,” 1951
    - United Europe, 1946-1948
  - Committee on the Atlantic Commission, 1951
  - Council of Europe, 1951 (Box 45)
  - Curtis, Lionel
    - Circular letters, 1948
    - Correspondence
      - 1945-1947, (5 folders)
      - 1949-1952, (7 folders) (Box 46)
      - 1953 (Box 47)
  - Curtis, Lionel
    - Death of, 1955
    - Miscellany, 1944-1952, undated
    - Scrapbook, 1943-1951, undated
    - Speeches and writings
      - Federation ou Guerre, 1945
      - General, 1940-1952
      - The Open Road to Freedom, 1950
      - The Political Repercussions of Atomic Power, 1949
      - Windows of Freedom, 1952
  - Denmark, 1951 (Box 48)
  - Dieterlen, Pierre, 1950-1952
  - England, 1949-1952, (3 folders)
  - Euler, William D., 1950-1951
  - Executive Committee minutes
    - 1950
    - 1951-1952, (4 folders) (Box 49)
  - Federal Union, International, 1950-1951
  - Film, “One and One Makes Three,” 1951
  - Foreign, 1950-1953
  - France, 1949-1952 (Box 50)
  - Freedom and Union, 1952-1953
  - Friends of Atlantic Union, 1952-1953
  - General
    - 1949-1950, (4 folders)
    - 1951-1953, undated, (4 folders) (Box 51)
  - Gillette, Guy Mark, 1951
  - Gouin, Leon-Mercier, 1951-1952
  - Griessemer, Tom O., 1951
  - Head, Henry William Nugent
    - Miscellany, 1955
    - Trip to England, 1951
  - Italy, 1951 (Box 52)
  - La Grange, Amaury de, 1951-1953
  - Leather, Edwin H. C., 1950-1952
  - Lindsay, Kenneth, 1950-1953
  - London, England, meeting, 1953
  - Macadam, Ivison S., 1950-1952
  - McCormick, Anne O'Hare, 1952-1953
  - Memphis, Tenn., convention, 1951
  - Moodie, Helen, 1951-1952
  - Netherlands, 1949-1953
  - Norway, 1950-1951
  - Printed matter, 1951-1955
  - Roberts, Owen J.
    - General, 1950-1952, (2 folders)
    - Trip to England, 1951-1953 (Box 53)
  - Robertson, Wishart McLain, 1950-52
  - Stewart, Alistair, 1951-1952
  - Streit, Clarence K., 1950-1951
  - Sweden, 1950-1951
  - Swinton, Kurt R., 1950-1951
  - United Europe Movement, 1948-1950
  - Van Lidth de Jeude, Jonkhur, 1950-1952
  - Van Nierop, Hendrik A., 1950-1953
  - Waldorf Astoria, New York, N.Y., dinner, 1951
  - Watson-Armstrong, William H., 1951-1952
- Part III: General Correspondence, 1949-1968 (Box 54-94)
  Letters, telegrams, reports, memoranda, minutes, and related material.
  Arranged by year and therein alphabetically by name of correspondent or subject.
  - 1949, (8 folders) (Box 54)
  - 1950
    - A-S, (23 folders)
    - T-W, (3 folders) (Box 55)
  - 1951, (9 folders)
  - 1952
    - A-Hern, (9 folders)
    - Herr-Ko, (10 folders) (Box 56)
    - Kr-Ly, (7 folders) (Box 57)
    - Mc-Moo, (8 folders) (Box 58)
    - Mor-Ox, (7 folders) (Box 59)
    - Pa-Rob, (9 folders) (Box 60)
    - Roc-Sq, (9 folders) (Box 61)
    - St-V, (8 folders) (Box 62)
    - Wa-Y, (7 folders) (Box 63)
  - 1953 (Box 64)
    - A-J, (11 folders)
    - K-R, (8 folders) (Box 65)
    - S-Z, (8 folders) (Box 66)
  - 1954
    - A-Bl, (3 folders)
    - Bo-G, (6 folders) (Box 67)
    - H-Mc, (10 folders) (Box 68)
    - M-R, (9 folders) (Box 69)
    - S-Y, (7 folders) (Box 70)
  - 1955
    - A
    - B-E, (6 folders) (Box 71)
    - F-K, (8 folders) (Box 72)
    - L-O, (7 folders) (Box 73)
    - O-T, (8 folders) (Box 74)
    - U-Y, (4 folders) (Box 75)
  - 1956
    - A-B, (5 folders)
    - C-H, (6 folders) (Box 76)
    - H-N, (10 folders) (Box 77)
    - O-R, (5 folders) (Box 78)
    - S-Z, (8 folders) (Box 79)
  - 1957 (Box 80)
    - A-H, (9 folders)
    - I-Roo, (9 folders) (Box 81)
    - Rop-Y, (6 folders) (Box 82)
  - 1958
    - A-C, (3 folders)
    - D-M, (13 folders) (Box 83)
    - N-Schm, (8 folders) (Box 84)
    - Scho-Z, (7 folders) (Box 85)
  - 1959
    - A-B, (3 folders)
    - C-Mc, (12 folders) (Box 86)
    - M-Z, (15 folders) (Box 87)
  - 1960 (Box 88)
    - A-G, (4 folders)
    - H-W, (9 folders) (Box 89)
  - 1961
    - A-V, (19 folders)
    - W-Z, (2 folders) (Box 90)
  - 1962, (11 folders)
  - 1963, (20 folders)
  - 1964
    - A-L, (7 folders)
    - M-S, (4 folders) (Box 91)
  - 1965, (9 folders)
  - 1966
    - A-Mc, (13 folders)
    - M-Z, (10 folders) (Box 92)
  - 1967
    - A-E, (5 folders)
    - F-R, (14 folders) (Box 93)
    - S-W, (5 folders) (Box 94)
  - 1968, (14 folders)
- Part III: Subject File, 1947-1968 (Box 95-122)
  Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, and related material.
  - American Association For United Nations Resolution, 1953 (Box 95)
  - American Legion, 1950-1955
  - American Veterans Committee, 1966
  - Atlantic Council, 1961, (2 folders)
  - Atlantic Council of the United States, 1963-1967
  - Atlantic Exploratory Convention, 1949-1957
  - Atlantic Institute, Paris, France, meeting, 1960-1961 (Box 96)
  - Background report, 1950
  - Blackwelder, Justin
    - Field work, 1957
    - Résumé, 1961-1967
  - Board of directors, minutes, 1949-1950, (2 folders)
  - Board of governors (Box 97)
    - Committees, 1956
    - Congress, 1961
    - Minutes
      - 1950-1951, (2 folders)
      - 1951-1955, (2 folders) (Box 98)
      - 1955-1960, (2 folders) (Box 99)
  - Brief for and against the Federal Union plan of Clarence K. Streit, undated
  - Buffalo, N.Y., branch, 1957-1959
  - Bylaws, 1949-1958, (3 folders)
  - Central Intelligence Agency, Justin Blackwelder, 1952-1953
  - Chapter programs, 1954
  - Checklist of materials relating to the International Trade Organization and the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, 1950
  - Circulars, lists, and related notes, 1956-1961, (4 folders) (Box 100)
  - Citizens convention, 1953-1954
  - Communism, 1953-1954
  - Conference Group of the United States, National Organization on the United Nations, 1954
  - Conference Upon Research and Education, 1954-1960 (Box 101)
  - Congress, 1952-1959
  - Congressional relations
    - Atlantic Commission, 1951-1952
    - Atlantic Union Resolution, 1950
    - Bills, resolutions, and reports, 1947-1958
    - Congressional Record, 1958-1960
    - Copies of lobbying report, 1952
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1951-1960, (4 folders)
      - Replies, 1952 (Box 102)
    - Drafts, joint resolutions, 1959-1960
    - Government commission report, 1958-1959
    - Hearings
      - House Committee on Foreign Affairs, 1960-1966, (2 folders)
      - House of Representatives, 1967
      - Resolutions, 1955, (2 folders)
      - Senate Resolution 57, 1950 (Box 103)
      - Testimony, Foreign Relations Committee, 1955
      - Witnesses, 1955
    - Letters from senators
      - General, 1956
      - Resolution, 1954-1955
        - A-H, (2 folders)
        - I-Z, (2 folders) (Box 104)
    - Letters to senators
      - General, 1956
      - Resolution, 1954-1955, (4 folders)
    - Letters from representatives
      - General, 1956
      - Resolution, 1954-1955, (4 folders)
    - Letters to representatives (Box 105)
      - General, 1956
      - Resolution, 1954-1955, (4 folders)
    - National Political Committee, 1950-1952
    - Political action, 1952
    - Replies to Hale Boggs, 1955
    - Resolutions
      - Draft, 1955-1956
      - General, 1955
      - Hartley, Livingston, material, 1950-1952
      - Miscellaneous, 1955
    - Senate Concurrent Resolution 36, 1951-1952 (Box 106)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1955, (2 folders)
    - State Department and White House, 1949-1956, (3 folders)
  - Delegates to Atlantic Union Convention, undated
  - Disarmament, 1957-1958
  - Dulles, John Foster, 1953-1957
  - European Free Trade Association, 1967-1968
  - Executive Committee
    - Board material, 1954
    - Minutes (Box 107)
      - 1949-1950, (3 folders)
      - 1951-1952, (3 folders) (Box 108)
      - 1956-1960 (Box 109)
  - Federal Union, Inc., 1956-1966
  - Ford Foundation, 1953
  - Forms, petitions for chapter charters, undated
  - Foundations, 1948
  - Freedom Studies Center, 1966
  - Future of the Committee, 1960
  - Inquiries, 1961
  - Institute of Significant Affairs, 1966
  - Jackson Committee, President's Committee on International Informational Activities, 1953
  - Kentuckiana branch, 1947
  - Keymen and chapter officers, 1953-1955
  - Lease agreement, 1953-1961
  - Literature requests, 1952-1954 (Box 110)
  - Match folder, 1950-1957
  - Membership campaigns, 1949-1950
  - Memphis, Tenn., branch, 1951
  - Minnesota branch, 1951
  - Minutes, bylaws and legal papers, 1949-1955, (2 folders)
  - National Council (Box 111)
    - Acquaintances in Congress, 1951-1953
    - Correspondence
      - General
        - 1949, (3 folders)
        - 1950
          - A-G, (2 folders)
          - H-W, (3 folders) (Box 112)
        - 1951-1957, (4 folders)
      - Acceptances (Box 113)
        - 1948-1950, (10 folders)
        - 1951-1957, (9 folders) (Box 114)
      - Invitations (Box 115)
        - General, 1949-1950
        - Unanswered, 1952-1953, (3 folders)
        - Regrets
          - 1949-1950, (5 folders)
          - 1951-1957, (9 folders) (Box 116)
        - Resignations, 1949-1953
        - Suspended
          - 1949-1950, (2 folders)
          - 1951-1952, (2 folders) (Box 117)
    - Form letters, undated
    - Lists, 1951-1953
    - Members by congressional districts, undated
    - Nominations, 1952
    - Procedure for handling files, undated
  - New York branch
    - Correspondence, 1951-1952, (7 folders)
    - Chapter activity, 1952 (Box 118)
    - Financial papers, 1950-1953
    - Membership Committee, 1953
  - North Atlantic Treaty Organization
    - General, 1953-1956, (2 folders)
    - Parliamentary meetings, 1956-1957
  - Organization For Economic Cooperation and Development, 1961
  - Planned Parenthood, 1965
  - Policy Committee, 1953
  - Political Committee (Box 119)
    - Acceptances, 1952
    - Memoranda, 1950-1952
    - Minutes and agenda, 1951-1952, (2 folders)
  - Political convention strategy, 1952
  - Population Association of America, 1965-1967
  - Population Reference Bureau, 1959-1968
  - Primaries, selecting delegates to national political conventions, 1952, (2 folders)
  - Psychological Strategy Board, 1952
  - Public relations, 1949-1950, (6 folders) (Box 120)
  - Publicity, 1949-1953
  - Radio Free Europe, 1952-1953
  - Reports, 1952
  - Roper Public Opinion Research Center, 1967-1968
  - Sierra Club, 1966-1967 (Box 121)
  - Stationery, undated
  - Statistics and charts, 1947-1956
  - Stocks, 1960-1961